Residence: (817) 478-1234 • Mobile: (817) 999-1234 • abc@aol.com

FIRE CAPTAIN

With Track Record of Strengthening Firefighting and Rescue Operations and Success in Providing the Community of Dallas, TX with 25+ Years of Excellent Public Service

Dedicated Fire Captain with more than 25 years of progressively responsible experience in the public service area. Strong qualifications in budgeting, personnel affairs, training, resource management, public safety, and emergency response. Well-developed leadership and analytical skills as evidenced by ability to continuously improve fire/rescue operations and emergency medical services. Reputation for strong work ethic and uncompromising devotion to service.

SPECIFIC SKILL AREAS

- Staff Development & Leadership
- Emergency Response Procedures
- Firefighting Techniques
- Fire Prevention & Enforcement
- Facility & Equipment Maintenance

- Time & Resource Allocation
- Budget Planning & Management
- Policy & Procedure Development
- Coaching, Training & Mentoring
- Public Education Programs

AWARDS & RECOGNITION

Meritorious Service Award – by Dallas Fire-Rescue Department (2006)

Person of the Year, "Outstanding Community Service" – by the City of Mansfield (2006)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

DALLAS FIRE-RESCUE DEPARTMENT, Dallas, TX

1981 - 2007

Fire Captain (2004–Present) Fire Lieutenant (1991–2004) Driver Engineer (1985-1991) Second Driver (1984-1985)

Fire Rescue Officer (1981-1984)

Promoted rapidly through strict promotion requirements to handle increasingly responsible positions, culminating in supervisory duty for staff of 12 employees. Hold key accountability for policy and procedure enforcement, emergency responses, station expenditures, facility and equipment inspection, personnel training, performance evaluations, and regulatory documentation and filing. **Selected Accomplishments:**

TEAM BUILDING & LEADERSHIP

- Demonstrate tact and diplomacy in responding to citizen's complaints against firefighters and allegations of misconduct, applying corrective strategies on minor infractions and stricter measures on more serious allegations.
- Used Employee Evaluation program that enhanced targeting of strengths/weaknesses and resulted in measurable, sustainable performance improvements.
- Earned high level of loyalty from staff and maintained excellent retention rate through fair, consistent
 evaluations and modeling effective on-the-job performance.



Professional Experience Continued

CRISIS MANAGEMENT & RESPONSE

- Repeatedly recognized by citizens, community groups, and supervisors for quick-thinking, calm, and correct response to a multitude of crisis and emergency situations, both in the field and as a Captain.
- Assist with in-service training programs for department personnel. Personally delivered well-received comprehensive program on Flashover Survival Training.

COMMUNITY RELATIONS & INVOLVEMENT

- Built goodwill between citizens and fire department over 25-year period, with emphasis on public education programs and community service initiatives.
- Invited to participate in assessment program for fire departments in other cities and states. Served as
 consultant to the Atlanta Fire Department, providing recommendations on professional development
 and personnel assessment techniques.

EDUCATION & TRAINING

PRAIRIE VIEW A&M UNIVERSITY, Prairie View, TX Bachelor of Arts, Mass Communication

Selected Professional Development Coursework:

Management Skills Development • Manager's Development • Flashover Survival Training • Instructional Techniques for Company Officers • Basic Officer School

Professional Certifications:

- Aircraft Rescue Firefighter, 2007
- Intermediate Firefighter, 2007

- CPR & First Aid, 2007
- Fire Ground Safety Officer, 2005

AFFILIATIONS & COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT

Member – Black Firefighters Association of Dallas (1985–Present)

Member – Faithful Friend's Missionary (1994–Present)

Member – Common Ground Network (1994–Present)

Member – Omega Psi Phi Fraternity (1981–Present)

COMPUTER SKILLS

Versed in: Windows OS, Microsoft Office, Internet, and email.







America's #1 Online Resume Builder

With Cover Letters

- Easy-to-use, guides you through step-by-step
- Resume templates, writing samples and tips
- One-click designs for the professional look you want
- Start from scratch or upload your resume



Already have an account?











Phone and Chat Hours: 7 Days a Week 6am to midnight EST



Write a resume - in minutes

Your resume is often your first and only chance to make a great impression on an employer. Managers will scan your resume for just 10 seconds to see if you're right for the job.

That's why your resume needs to be attractive and stand out. It needs to be well-written and highlight your skills to your best advantage.

The problem is most people don't know how to write a great resume and don't have the design skills to make it look professional.

- Our Resume Builder is designed to make resume-writing fast and easy.
- We match you with the right template and, in just one click, you can choose a professional design that will help you win the job.
- Our unique Text Tuner™ allows you to choose from hundreds of expert-written examples - no more writer's block!

Get the "most impressive resume builder on the market today". There's no risk; no obligation. We're so confident that you'll love our resume builder that you can try it for FREE.

According to our partners..."the most impressive resume builder on the market today."

onTargetiobs

YAHOO! hotjobs EmploymentGuide.com

Ret-Temps Joined

Customer Reviews

Job.com

"I was completely unaware of what companies are looking for in a resume. This product helped me word and format my professional resume and the examples were extremely useful. Overall, this is a great product. I would highly recommend these services." - A. Danihels

"This resume tool is so much better than templates - just upload or enter your resume content and you get your choice of designs. It's magical! Anyone can benefit from this tool: from students to executives!" - Belinda Yanda

View more reviews >



